Guide to the Cuban Revolution Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Other Films, Photographs, Postcards, and Printed Materials, 1955-[1968]; Series III
  - CBC Films, 1964
    - Alternative Title: Images of Havana and Fidel Castro's Personal Interactions with the Public, 1964; Running Time: 00:16:10
      Rally of young students and general public on the corner of Galiano Street and San Rafael Boulevard in the municipality of Centro Habana, at which a number of orators speak to the crowd from the roof of a car equipped with large speakers. The street corner is noteworthy for being the place where the famously posh department store called El Encanto was destroyed and set ablaze by counterrevolutionary arsonists (possibly under the employment of the store's private owners on April 13, 1961, six days before the Bay of Pigs Invasion). The resulting open space where the store once stood was made into a park named for the employee who died in the blaze and subsequently became a revolutionary martyr, Fe del Valle.
      El Comandante Fidel Castro visiting a school accompanied by a large caravan of cars.
      El Comandante Fidel Castro conversing with a group of citizens in a town close to the capital; among the citizens, there is one man who wears the consignia of the Escuelas Básicas de Instrucción Revolucionaria (EBIR), or primary schools for the ideological education of adult workers with previously acquired low levels of scholastic achievement.
      Portion of a cabaret show with a number of dancers, including the famous rumba dancer Ana Gloria Varona, singers, and an orchestra interpreting a cha-cha-cha. The final credits presented through the use of small boards held by the performers on stage show that other famed entertainers such as Jorge Pais, Pipo de Armas, Pedro del Valle and the quartet Los Bucaneros, also participated although they do not appear in film.
      Película en blanco y negro, sin sonido, tomada en distintas locaciones de la ciudad de La Habana, donde pueden apreciarse las siguientes escenas:
      Concentración de jóvenes estudiantes y pueblo en general en la esquina de las calles Galiano y San Rafael (Municipio Centro Habana), donde dos oradores realizan discursos desde encima de un automóvil con altoparlantes. Es la esquina donde estuvo el centro comercial El Encanto (incendiada por sabotaje el 13 de abril de 1961) y posteriormente el parque Fe del Valle.
      El Comandante Fidel Castro de visita en una escuela y luego caravana de autos.
      El Comandante Fidel Castro conversando con un grupo de ciudadanos de un pueblo cercano a la capital; entre los congregados se observa alguien con el distintivo de las Escuelas Básicas de Instrucción Revolucionaria (EBIR).
      Parte de un espectáculo de cabaret donde aparecen bailarines –aparece la rumbera Ana Gloria Varona-, cantantes y orquesta interpretando Cha cha chá; por los créditos finales que presentan los artistas, al parecer también actuaron los conocidos Jorge Pais, Pipo de Armas, Pedro del Valle y el cuarteto Los Bucaneros, aunque no salen en el filme.
      - Original film [restricted], film reel (16mm) (Box 75)
      - Duplicating master [restricted], videotape (Betacam SP) (Box 75D1)
      - Duplicating master [restricted], videotape (Digital Betacam) (Box 75D2)
      - Use copy, optical disk (DVD) (Box 75U)
    - Alternative Title: Grounds of the Ana Betancourt School for Peasant Women, 1964; Running Time: 00:10:43
      Film has no sound. Original Reel 48-7.
      Filmed in Havana Province (Provincia Ciudad de La Habana).
      Black and white film taken in various locations of the military zone marked Unidad C-19 "Rubén Martínez Villena." Female students of the Ana Betancourt school, created by the revolutionary government for the education of peasant women, can be seen, as well as a daycare center, possibly for their children. The entrance to the military zone is guarded by an armed soldier and the grounds of the school located within the zone are both extensive and filled with trees, dense foliage and a number of buildings that serve as a dining room, dormitories, classrooms, and workshops. Several of the female students engage in diverse activities such as marching in military style, participating in a ceremony for the raising of the Cuban flag, and sitting in a classroom as they receive instruction. In addition, the film features views of a workshop where the students engage in the principal vocation for which the Ana Betancourt system was founded, that is, the cutting, sewing and tailoring of clothes. The sewing machines visible in the workshop are all from United States-manufacturer Singer. The final images of the film show a daycare center whose location is unclear in which children are seen playing in the courtyard while they are watched by a number of female daycare workers.
      The first Ana Betancourt school for teaching peasant women sewing and tailoring was founded at the end of 1959, with the first graduation ceremony in 1960. The first classes were held in a salon of the luxurious, once five-star Hotel Nacional and then transferred to an opulent mansion in Miramar abandoned by a wealthy family whose interests were jeopardized by the Revolution. As word got out about the opportunity to study in Havana with all boarding and matriculation costs paid by the government, the number of peasant women enrolled in the school ballooned from a few hundred to over 15,000 by 1960. Methods for the cutting and sewing of clothes developed at the school were given the name "Ana Betancourt" and patterns labeled with this name began to appear in women's magazines published by the revolutionary government organ known as the Federación de Mujeres Cubanas (FMC) as early as 1961.
      Película en blanco y negro, sin sonido, tomada en distintas locaciones de la Unidad C-19 "Rubén Martínez Villena" para alumnas Ana Betancourt y en un círculo infantil.
      La entrada de la unidad es custodiada por un militar armado y sus terrenos son extensos con numerosos árboles e incluye varias edificaciones (comedor, dormitorios, aulas y talleres). Se pueden observar a las alumnas en diversas actividades como marchando a la usanza de los militares, en el acto de arriar la bandera y en el aula recibiendo clases. También aparece el taller con máquinas de coser marca Singer, donde realizan las actividades de corte y costura.
      Aparece un círculo infantil, sin identificar, donde los niños juegan en el patio a la vista de las trabajadoras que los custodian.
      - Original film [restricted], film reel (16mm) (Box 76)
      - Duplicating master [restricted], videotape (Betacam SP) (Box 76D1)
      - Duplicating master [restricted], videotape (Digital Betacam) (Box 76D2)
      - Use copy, optical disk (DVD) (Box 76U)
    - Alternative Title: Scenes of the Hotel Habana Libre (formerly Havana Hilton), 1964; Running Time: 00:07:49
      Film has no sound. Original Reel 47-8.
      Filmed at the Hotel Habana Libre, previously known as the Havana Hilton before government expropriation in 1960 from owner Conrad Hilton; located in the Plaza de la Revolución municipality, city of Havana (La Habana).
      Black and white film taken in different locations of the hotel Habana Libre. They include the driveway of the front entrance to the hotel, which is being guarded by a heavily armed militia man; the interior lobby, where a number of hotel guests and employees can be seen, including one female attendant at the front desk who is dressed in military uniform and carrying a loaded pistol. Images of the elevator and swimming pool area taken from the top floors of the hotel.
      Película en blanco y negro, sin sonido, tomada en distintas locaciones del hotel, donde pueden apreciarse escenas de su entrada principal, donde un miliciano armado custodia el área; del interior en el lobby, donde aparecen huéspedes y empleados; al parecer una empleada vestida de militar y armada; en el elevador y una toma del área de la piscina desde pisos superiores.
      - Original film [restricted], film reel (16mm) (Box 77)
      - Duplicating master [restricted], videotape (Betacam SP) (Box 77D1)
      - Duplicating master [restricted], videotape (Digital Betacam) (Box 77D2)
      - Use copy, optical disk (DVD) (Box 77U)
    - Alternative Title: Miscellaneous Scenes of Life in Havana, 1964; Running Time: 00:27:21
      Film has no sound. Original Reel 48-9.
      Filmed in Havana, city proper, and other unidentified sites (La Habana y otros lugares sin identificar).
      Black and white film in which the following scenes appear:
      Students of the University of Havana as they are interviewed by Lisa, a Canadian Broadcasting Corporation reporter, in the Plaza Cadenas.
      A student of the Ana Betancourt school being interviewed.
      Large rolls of craft paper imported from the People's Republic of China.
      Fidel Castro conversing with villagers and a peasant family in the countryside.
      The interior of the old Woolworth store on Galiano Street and San Rafael Boulevard in Centro Havana.
      Reporter interviewing an armed guard at the entrance to the main telephone exchange, formerly owned by the Cuban Telephone Company (one of the first United States companies to be nationalized), located on Dragones and Aguila Streets in Centro Habana.
      Coastline to the east of El Morro Fortress; vistas of the entrance to Havana's harbor and adjacent grounds taken from a car traveling along the Avenida del Puerto; the enormous statue of Jesus Christ that overlooks the Bay of Havana and is located in the town of Casa Blanca; boats moored in the bay.
      Soft drink factory.
      A cafeteria located in one of Havana's various "five-and-dime" stores.
      Building housing the first air-conditioned movie theatre in Cuba, once known as Radiocentro (later renamed Cine Yara); the hotel Habana Libre and street scenes taken of the corner of 23rd and L streets in the neighborhood of Vedado where the strip known as La Rampa begins and where the Cine Yara is located.
      A reception for foreign guests, possibly held for visiting foreign journalists.
      Fidel Castro on a tour of the intensive cattle breeding farms he developed as a solution to the beef and milk crisis that began in the early years of the Revolution.
      Female students lined up on the sidewalk of a street in the Miramar district of Havana.
      Havana's international airport "José Martí."
      Cabaret where journalists engage a performer who is being interviewed.
      Exterior and interior of the Escuela de Superación "Fe del Valle," a school for the political education of citizens selected for membership in the Cuban Communist Party.
      Peasants shepherding cattle along a highway.
      Funerary procession preceding the burial of a number of unidentified people, headed by a musical band as it advances down G Street (also known as La Avenida de los Presidentes) in Vedado. The procession includes a number of military and civilian officials.
      Rural landscape.
      Película en blanco y negro, sin sonido, tomada en diferentes locaciones, donde pueden apreciarse:
      Estudiantes de la Universidad de La Habana, entrevistados en la Plaza Cadenas.
      Una estudiante de las Escuelas Ana Betancourt es entrevistada.
      Bobinas de papel de procedencia china.
      Fidel Castro conversando con vecinos de un poblado y con familia campesina.
      Interior del Ten Cents de Galiano y San Rafael.
      Periodista entrevistando a custodio armado frente a la central telefónica de la calle Dragones y Águila.
      Litoral al este del Morro; vistas de entrada a la bahía y terrenos aledaños desde un auto que rueda por la Avenida del Puerto; estatua del cristo, barcos, etc.
      Fábrica de refrescos.
      Cafetería.
      Edificios Radiocentro (hoy cine Yara), hotel Habana Libre y escenas callejeras en la esquina de las calles 23 y L en el barrio de El Vedado.
      Recepción nutrida donde participan los periodistas.
      Fidel Castro en recorrido por centro de ganadería intensiva.
      Niñas estudiantes en filas por acera de una calle en Miramar.
      Aeropuerto.
      Cabaret donde comparten periodistas y entrevistada.
      Exterior e interior de Escuela de superación Fe del Valle.
      Campesinos arreando ganado por una carretera.
      Entierro de varias personas, encabezado por banda de música por la calle G de El Vedado, en el cual se observan numerosos militares y civiles.
      Paisaje rural.
      - Original film [restricted], film reel (16mm) (Box 78)
      - Duplicating master [restricted], videotape (Betacam SP) (Box 78D1)
      - Duplicating master [restricted], videotape (Digital Betacam) (Box 78D2)
      - Use copy, optical disk (DVD) (Box 78U)
    - Alternative Title: Miscellaneous Scenes of Life and Buildings in Havana, 1964; Running Time: 00:19:53
      Film has no sound. Original Reel 48-10.
      Filmed in The municipalities of El Cerro, Centro Habana, and Old Havana (located within the capital) and the municipality of Eastern Havana, part of Havana province (Provincia Ciudad de La Habana).
      Black and white film taken in different locations, in which the following scenes are observed:
      An unidentified person reading a book titled El Partido Marxista Leninista.
      An unidentified person being interviewed.
      Poster on a wall denouncing the "10 pirate missions" of the Central Intelligence Agency (CIA) against Cuba, with a specific description of the site of attack.
      Woman sitting at a sewing machine while a small girl looks on.
      Street scenes near the enormous nineteenth-century market known as the Mercado Único de Cuatro Caminos that lies between the municipalities of El Cerro and Old Havana on Cristina Street.
      Interior shots and scenes of worshippers in the Catholic Church of San Nicolás, located near Monte Street, in Centro Habana.
      Exterior shots of the Church of San Nicolás, as well as its surroundings, including scenes of worshippers who just attended mass, and patrons of a bar that features an old-fashioned vitrola (jukebox) and recycled bottles of the capitalist era.
      El Morro Fortress and La Cabaña military zone at the entrance to the Bay of Havana.
      The building once known as Radiocentro (now the Cine Yara) on the corner of 23rd and L streets in Vedado, taken from the balcony of the Hotel Habana Libre.
      Alguien hojeando un libro que se titula "El Partido Marxista Leninista".
      Alguien sin identificar que es entrevistado.
      Cartel en una pared denunciando 10 misiones piratas de la Agencia Central de Inteligencia (CIA) contra Cuba, con expresión de los lugares de ejecución.
      Mujer en una máquina de cocer mientras una niña observa.
      Escenas callejeras alrededor del Mercado Único de Cuatro Caminos en el límite de los actuales municipios del Cerro y La Habana Vieja.
      Vistas interiores y escenas típicas de feligreses en la iglesia católica de San Nicolás. Vista exterior de la iglesia de San Nicolás y sus alrededores.
      Bar que queda muy cercano a la iglesia con vitrola y parroquianos.
      El Morro, La Cabaña y entrada de la bahía de La Habana.
      Edificio de Radiocentro y esquina de las calles 23 y L en el Vedado, tomadas desde un balcón del Hotel Habana Libre.
      - Original film [restricted], film reel (16mm) (Box 79)
      - Duplicating master [restricted], videotape (Betacam SP) (Box 79D1)
      - Duplicating master [restricted], videotape (Digital Betacam) (Box 79D2)
      - Use copy, optical disk (DVD) (Box 79U)
  - Photographs of buildings, roads, building sites, and views of native life [apparently prepared by the Ministerio de Obras Publicas, in connection with the Seventh Congreso de la Union Internacional de Arquitectos, [1963] (Box 80, Folder 1-3)
  - Postcards of public buildings and streets in Cuba, [1963] (Box 80, Folder 4-7)
  - Printed material and other assorted papers
    See: Box 81
    - Manifesto del 26 de Julio al Pueblo de Cuba, Nos. 1 and 2, 1955 (Box 80, Folder 8)
    - "This is What We are Fighting For" [typescript of a Fidel Castro speech in English; incomplete], [1957?] (Box 80, Folder 9)
    - "Denuncia de Comandante Raul Castro Ante La Juventud del Mundo", 1958 June 27 (Box 80, Folder 10)
    - Sanchez, Juan Nuiry. Speech or declaration from Sierra Maestra [carbon copy], 1958 October 26 (Box 80, Folder 11)
    - Ejercito Rebelde, Seccion del Cafe [rules for the functioning of local offices signed by Dr. Humberto Sorí Marin and Dr. Raul Chibras; letter transmitting resolutions and set of rules, 1958 (Box 80, Folder 12)
    - Verde Olivo, 1959 July 20, August 8
    - Citizens for a Free Cuba [form letter signed by Spruille Braden, [1963-1968] (Box 80, Folder 13)
    - Boletin Deportivo [no. 8], 1966 August (Box 80, Folder 14)
    - Carta Abierta Al Exilio Cubano. "Por La Unidad Militar para la Guerra" [letter to Cuban exiles], undated (Box 80, Folder 15)
    - Cuba Rebelde [appeal to the people], undated (Box 80, Folder 16)
    - Frente Civico Revolucionario de Lucha Contra la Tirania al Pueblo de Cuba, undated (Box 80, Folder 17)
    - 26th of July Proclamation issued by Raul Chivas and Felipe Pazos (Orthodox Party) endorsed by Castro but never put into effect [photostat], undated (Box 80, Folder 18)
    - Clipping re: statement of Duvalier on Alliance for Progress, undated (Box 80, Folder 19)
    - Verde Olivo, 1959 July 20, August 3 (Box 81)
- Additional Material, 1970; Accession 2011-M-004
  - Transcript and translation of David Stone's film, Compañeras y Compañeros, made by members of the Weathermen group for Adolfas Mekas, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
- Additional Material, 1959-1961; Accession 2016-M-080
  This accession consists of printed materials produced in Cuba during the Cuban revolution, dated 1959-1961.
  - Cumpliremos!: Temas sobre la revolución para los alfabetizadores, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Alfabeticemos: Manual para el alfabetizador, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Aprendo a leer y escribir, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Alfabetización, nacionalización de la enseñanza, Circa 1960 (Box 1, Folder 4)